Guide to the Allyson K. Duncan Papers, 1914-2019 RL.11642
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allyson K. Duncan Papers
1914-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duncan, Allyson K.
RL.11642
7.0 Linear Feet
0.06 Gigabytes
Allyson Kay Duncan is a U.S. Circuit Judge of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. She is the Fourth Circuit's first female African American judge. This collection consists largely of personal and professional correspondence from Duncan's nomination, induction, and service on the Fourth Circuit, with letters from family, friends, and colleagues across the legal profession. The bulk of the collection dates from the 2000s, but includes some assorted materials from her work as an attorney for Kilpatrick Stockton and the NC Utilities Commission in the 1990s.
Biographical / Historical
Allyson Kay Duncan (b. 1951) was born in Durham and attended Hampton University (BA, 1972) and Duke University (JD, 1975). She worked for the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (1978-1986) and was a professor at NC Central School of Law (1986-1990) before being appointed by Gov. James Martin as Associate Judge to the North Carolina Court of Appeals in 1990. After losing the next election, she was appointed to the North Carolina Utilities Commission in 1991, where she worked until joining the Kilpatrick Stockton firm in 1998. In 2003 she was elected as the first African American president of the North Carolina Bar Association, and was also nominated by President George W. Bush to fill a vacancy on the Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals. She was confirmed by the U.S. Senate in July 2003 and inducted to the court in August 2003, where she continues to serve (as of 2018). Duncan was the first African American woman to join the Fourth Circuit.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted: Donor must be contacted for use permission prior to accessing the collection. Access will be unrestricted upon the death of the donor. Contact Research Services to request permission to access this collection.
Provenance
The Allyson K. Duncan Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018 and 2019.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of Duncan's correspondence, including both personal and professional communications with family, friends, and colleagues, including other judges such as Clarence Thomas, John Roberts, Diane Wood, J. Harvie Wilkinson III, William Traxler Jr., and several others; press clippings and articles about Duncan's activities as president for the NC Bar Association and her appointment to and service on the U.S. Court of Appeals (4th Circuit); copies of speeches and programs from her various professional activities for Duke Law School and NC Central Law School, among other appearances; assorted materials from her work for the NC Utilities Commission and Kilpatrick Stockton law firm; her diplomas and awards; some family history materials from her parents and other relatives, including her aunt Helen Blackburn and uncle Armour Blackburn; and assorted photographs, largely unlabelled. Also includes published opinions for the NC Court of Appeals and NC Utility Commission and writings by Duncan.
Conditions Governing Access
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services for the production of listening or viewing copies.
Judges -- United States -- Correspondence; Judges -- North Carolina; Thomas, Clarence, 1948-; United States. Court of Appeals (4th Circuit); North Carolina Bar Association; Duke University. School of Law -- Alumni and alumnae; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Duncan, Allyson K.; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
- Correspondence, 2003-2015; 12 folders (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Personal and professional correspondence saved by Duncan, documenting her communications with friends and family; her law clerks and other chamber staff; other judges, including Clarence Thomas, John Roberts, Diane Wood, J. Harvie Wilkinson III, William Traxler Jr., and several others. Much of the correspondence documents Duncan's personal activities, including gifts, special occasions, and hobbies. There are also letters congratulating her on various speeches, awards, and appointments. Separate folders contain letters celebrating her NC Bar Association election and her appointment to the Fourth Circuit.
- Personal correspondence, 2003-2016 (Box 4)
  Primarily correspondence for personal appearances in classes and on panels, including moot court competitions.
- Biographies, resumes, and headshots, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
- North Carolina Utilities Commission, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  Includes testimony transcripts; an article about Duncan as Utilities Commissioner written during the Clarence Thomas/Anita Hill investigation; a copy of her appointment; and a celebratory Black History Month publication.
- Kilpatrick Stockton law firm, 1998-2003 (Box 1)
- North Carolina Bar Association election and service as president, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
  Press articles and coverage of Duncan's election and term as first African American president of the NCBA.
- United States Court of Appeals (4th Circuit) nomination and investiture, 2003; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Press coverage, editorials, and other materials supporting Duncan's nomination, hearing, and investiture to the Fourth Circuit.
- United States Court of Appeals (4th Circuit) nomination and investiture, 2002-2003; 10 folders (Box 4)
  Questionnaires, letters of support, forms, transcripts, memoranda, and oath of office for the Fourth Circuit.
- United States Court of Appeals (4th Circuit) service and press coverage, 2005-2012 (Box 1)
  News coverage about Fourth Circuit activities and rulings, some quote Duncan.
- Congratulatory letters celebrating Duncan's NCBA presidency and nomination to the Fourth Circuit, 2002-2003; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Damon J. Keith subject file, 2004-2009 (Box 1)
- Hampton University subject file, 1990-2014 (Box 1)
- Duke Law School subject file, 1975-2014 (Box 1)
- Duncan, A. "The Richmond Decision: What the Supreme Court Did NOT Say," Trumpet newsletter, 1989 Spring (Box 1)
- Duncan, A. "Diversity Revisited and the Wisdom of Crowds," NC State Bar Journal article, 2010 Spring (Box 1)
- Profiles and press coverage re: Duncan, 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
- Profiles and press coverage re: Duncan, 1977-2019; 8 folders (Box 5)
  Includes two resumes and a photograph of Duncan with George H. W. Bush.
- Profiles and Press Coverage re: Duncan, 2003-11-28 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11642-VHS-0001)
  UNC_TV North Carolina People episode #3321 featuring Duncan
  Conditions Governing Access
  RESTRICTED: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
- Programs and events, 2003-2014; 7 folders (Box 2)
  Programs, pamphlets, and other materials collected by Duncan documentating her participation in various public events, including speeches and ceremonies. Files also contain invitations, logistical arrangements, and some drafts of her remarks as the invited speaker.
- Programs and events, 2004-2017 (Box 4)
  Programs and brochures from ceremonies and events. Includes a certificate for a Women's History Month celebration, material from a Campbell University School of Law convocation, and a commencement program from the University of Connecticut (2006), from which Duncan received an honorary degree.
- Programs and events, 2012 (Oversize-folder 1)
  Harvard Law School Charles Hamilton Houston Institute for Race and Justice signed conference poster.
- Photographs of Duncan with other judges, including Chief Justice John Roberts and Justice Clarence Thomas, 2000s (Box 2)
- Personal photographs of Duncan and other family members, 1950s-2000s (Box 2)
- Robert and Anne Duncan legal deeds, photocopied documents, 1914-1952 (Box 2)
- Armour and Helen Blackburn memorials and tributes, 1948-2011 (Box 2)
  Includes Armour Blackburn's 1948 diploma from Columbia University.
- Allyson Duncan awards, diplomas, commissions, and appointments, 1975-2002; 2 folders (Box 3)
  Includes Duncan's Duke Law School diploma, her appointment to the N.C. Court of Appeals (1990), her appointment to the Board of Public Telecommunications Commissioners, and her admission as an attorney to the U.S. Court of Appeals (4th Circuit), the NC State Bar, the North Carolina Eastern District Court, and the U.S. Supreme Court.
- Digital photos of plaques, 2018-2019; 57 digital files extracted from an optical disc; approximately 60 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11642-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 7)
  Digital image files in JPEG format.
- North Carolina Court of Appeals cases, 1990; 2 folders (Box 4)
  Decisions and dissenting and concurring opionions.
- North Carolina Utility Commission, 1991-1998; 3 folders (Box 4)
  Dissenting opinions.
- Orders and briefs, 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  Reference materials.
- American Law Institute membership documents, 2011 (Box 4)
- Writings by Duncan, 1978-2010; 2 folders (Box 4)
  Briefs and articles by Duncan.